"June 19."
"19 Haziran.
"My first meeting with Franz Bonaparta."
Franz Bonaparta'yla ilk görüşmem.
"RF179. A very quiet man."
RF179. Çok ketum bir adam.
"Refined manner. Wears a suit."
Zarif bir adam. Takım elbise giyiyor.
"Children assemble for book readings in the afternoon."
Öğleden sonra kitap okuma için çocuklarla buluşma var"
Where do you want to go?
İstikamet neresi?
-To the border. -Which one?
-Sınır. -Ne sınırı?
The Czech border.
Çek sınırı.
Get in.
Atla.
Thank you.
Teşekkürler.
Children assemble for book readings in the afternoon.
Öğleden sonra kitap okuma için çocuklarla buluşma var"
A very eerie mansion. Red Rose Mansion.
Çok ürkütücü bir malikâne. Kırmızı Güllü Malikâne.
P. Břevnov W.
P. Břevnov W.
Steeple to the left.
Solda çan kulesi var.
Weather vane to the right.
Sağda rüzgâr gülü var.
Human dignity. Experiments.
İnsan onuru. Deneyler.
Magnificent experiments.
Görkemli deneyler.
Depravation of dignity.
İnsan onuru kırılıyor.
Where are you from?
Nerelisin?
I mean, what country are you from?
Yani hangi ülkeden geldin?
I don't know if Japanese people like this,
Japonlar sever mi bilmiyorum
but have it.
ama al.
It's left over from my lunch.
Öğle yemeğimden kalanlar.
-Thank you, but-- -Eat!
-Teşekkürler ama… -Ye.
You look like you're about to collapse.
Bayılacakmış gibi görünüyorsun.
My wife keeps nagging me to go on a diet.
Karım beni diyet yapmaya zorlayıp duruyor.
Thank you for this.
Teşekkürler.
Go on. Eat up.
Hadi, ye.
You'll never make it through a long journey if you don't eat.
Yemek yemeden uzun bir yolculuğu atlatamazsın.
I've got to bring this journey to an end.
Bu yolculuğa bir son vermeliyim.
You're kidding!
Şaka yapıyorsun!
You let him go? You let Tenma leave?
Gitmesine izin mi verdin? Tenma'nın gitmesine izin mi verdin?
-Yes. -Why didn't you stop him?
-Evet. -Onu neden durdurmadın?
I think you know he's not someone who can be stopped.
Onu durdurmanın mümkün olmadığını sanırım biliyorsun.
Yes, but--
Evet ama…
What's more, with Eva Heinemann missing, we're in a dire situation.
Dahası, Eva Heinemann'ın kaybolmasıyla çok kötü bir durumdayız.
Tenma escaped to save her.
Tenma onu kurtarmak için kaçmış.
That lawyer who called himself Baul,
Adının Baul olduğunu söyleyen o avukatın
I'm pretty sure he's the same man who tried to take my life at my office.
ofisimde beni öldürmeye çalışan adamla aynı kişi olduğuna adım gibi eminim.
He got close to me to get his hands on my father's notebook.
Babamın defterini ele geçirmek için benimle yakınlaştı.
That notebook must be pretty darn important.
O defter acayip önemli olmalı.
I'll be going now.
Ben gideyim.
Where to?
Nereye?
To where Tenma's going.
Tenma'nın gittiği yere.
Do you mean the Red Rose Mansion?
Kırmızı Güllü Malikâne'ye mi yani?
Where is it?
Orası nerede?
My father's notebook was filled with perplexing notes.
Babamın defteri kafa karıştıran notlarla dolu.
But I don't think this was in code.
Şifreli olduğunu sanmıyorum.
"Red rose mansion. P. Břevnov W."
"Kırmızı Güllü Malikâne. P. Břevnov B"
"P" stands for "Prague."
P harfinin açılımı Prag.
"W" stands for "west."
B harfinin açılımı batı.
To the west of the Prague suburb Břevnov.
Prag'ın batısındaki Břevnov banliyösü.
From there, you can see a steeple to the left and a weather vane to the right.
Oradan bakınca solda bir çan kulesi, sağda da rüzgâr gülü görülür.
I see.
Anlıyorum.
Hopefully, we'll find someone
Umarım o malikânede
at that mansion who can tell us something that solves all of this.
tüm bunları çözmemizi sağlayacak birini bulabiliriz.
But it's doubtful.
Ama şüphelerim var.
Wait.
Dur.
"Children assemble for book readings in the afternoon."
Öğleden sonra kitap okuma için çocuklarla buluşma var"
That was also in the notebook.
Defterde bu da yazıyordu.
Children from that time could tell us something!
O dönemin çocukları bize bir şey söyleyebilir.
Mr. Verdemann.
Verdemann.
I criticized you earlier for not stopping Tenma.
Tenma'yı durdurmadığın için sana sinirlenmiştim
But if I'd been in your shoes, I probably would've done the same.
ama senin yerinde olsaydım muhtemelen ben de aynı şeyi yapardım.
Come on. Let's go.
Hadi, gidelim.
THREE FROGS
ÜÇ KURBAĞA
I was here.
Buradaydım.
I lived in this neighborhood.
Bu mahallede yaşıyordum.
And…
Ve…
Welcome back.
Tekrar hoş geldin.
Are you okay, Nina?
İyi misin Nina?
I'm okay.
İyiyim.
I think you should give it up.
Bence pes etmelisin.
Every time we look, you get lost.
Ne zaman arasak kayboluyorsun.
No, I'm sure I'll remember.
Hayır, hatırlayacağımı sanmıyorum.
My brother told me what happened back then
Abim Üç Kurbağa'ya götürüldüğünde neler olduğunu,
After passing the station, he saw the city on the left
Karakolu geçtikten sonra solda şehri gördü.
and they traveled alongside the riverside trolley.
Nehir kenarı tramvayının yanından gitmişler.
Turn right here--
Buradan sağa!
Don't try it.
Deneme.
Keeping secrets from him is a no-no.
Ondan sır saklamak büyük ayıp.
Right, is it?
Sağ, değil mi?
What's wrong?
Ne oldu?
It's nothing.
Hiç.
What do you think? Do you see anything familiar?
Ne düşünüyorsun? Tanıdık bir şeyler var mı?
I'm not sure.
Tam bilmiyorum.
We'll never find it.
Asla bulamayacağız.
It happened so long ago, you'll never remember it!
Üzerinden uzun zaman geçti, hatırlaman mümkün değil!
Nina!
Nina!
A weather vane on the right.
Sağda bir rüzgâr gülü.
A church steeple on the left.
Solda da kilise çan kulesi.
Nina!
Nina!
The Red Rose Mansion.
Kırmızı Güllü Malikâne.
Is this the place?
Burası orası mı?
I'm not sure.
Tam bilmiyorum.
But… I know this place.
Ama burayı biliyorum.
I'm scared.
Korkuyorum.
What's that?
O ne?
It's like a door emerged from inside the wall.
Duvarın içinden bir kapı çıkmış sanki.
There's nothing here.
Burada hiçbir şey yok.
Nina?
Nina.
Nina!
Nina!
You demon!
Seni iblis!
The demon is dead.
İblis öldü.
How are you feeling?
Nasıl oldun?
Welcome back, Mr. Lipský.
Hoş geldiniz Bay Lipský.
Did you get an audience?
Seyirci çıktı mı?
No. Nobody watched, as usual.
Hayır, her zamanki gibi kimse izlemedi.
But they're such lovely puppets.
Ama kuklalarınız çok güzel.
What I'm making now is even lovelier.
Şu an yaptığım daha da güzel.
I can hardly wait to see it.
Görmeyi iple çekiyorum.
I'll bring it to you as soon as it's finished.
Biter bitmez sana getireceğim.
It's time for me to go to work.
Artık işe gitme vaktim geldi.
At the restaurant?
Restorana mı?
Yeah. I can't make a living off of these puppets.
Evet, bu kuklalarla geçinemiyorum.
I'm so sorry that I've been a burden to you for so long.
Bu kadar uzun süre size yük olduğum için çok özür dilerim.
No, I don't mind. Don't let it bother you.
Hayır, sorun değil. Canını sıkma.
Mr. Lipský, there's something I'd like to ask you.
Bay Lipský, sormak istediğim bir şey var.
What is it?
Nedir?
Three months ago
Üç ay önce
when you found me passed out and took me to the hospital…
baygın hâlde bulup beni hastaneye götürdüğünüzde…
Yes?
Evet.
What were you doing at that mansion?
O malikânede ne yapıyordunuz?
Nina?
Nina.
Nina!
Nina!
Answer me, Nina!
Cevap ver Nina!
What's the matter?
Ne oldu?
When I go to that mansion, I get ideas for my creations.
O malikâneye gittiğimde eserlerim için fikir buluyorum.
I'm not sure how to put it.
Nasıl söylesem?
But now, something else inspires me more…
Artık başka yerden ilham alıyorum.
Never mind. Anyway, don't worry about staying.
Boş ver, neyse. Kaldığın için çekinme.
You can stay here for as long as you like.
İstediğin kadar kalabilirsin.
Nina…
Nina…
May I come in?
Gelebilir miyim?
Of course.
Elbette.
You're well enough to get up?
Kalkacak kadar iyileştin mi?
Yes.
Evet.
Wow! This must be where the puppets are made.
Vay canına, kuklalar burada yapılıyor demek.
I never get an audience.
Hiç izleyicim olmuyor.
What kind of story do you tell?
Ne tür hikâye anlatıyorsunuz?
It's a story about a demon.
Bir iblisin hikâyesi.
What's wrong, Nina?
Ne oldu Nina?
Nothing…Please continue.
Hiç, devam edin lütfen.
A demon looking for a reason to destroy the world goes on a trip.
Dünyayı yok etmek isteyen bir iblis bir yolculuğa çıkıyor.
Along the way, he almost dies.
Yolculukta neredeyse ölüyor.
But a boy who happens upon him saves his life.
Ama ona rastlayan bir erkek çocuk iblisin hayatını kurtarıyor.
When the boy finds out who it was he saved,
Çocuk kimin hayatını kurtardığını öğrendiğinde
he chases after the demon.
iblisin peşine düşüyor.
His travels end when he finds the demon
Yolculuğunun sonunda iblisi buluyor
who he kills with a knife.
ve onu bıçakla öldürüyor.
I think it's pretty interesting, but nobody's interested in it.
Bence çok enteresan bir hikâye ama kimsenin ilgisini çekmiyor.
Are you all right, Nina?
İyi misin Nina?
That's probably what I would do.
Ben olsam ben de öyle yapardım.
That's what I would do.
Ben de öyle yapardım.
But I can't let him do that.
Ama böyle yapmasına izin veremem.
Nina?
Nina.
Any human…
Kim olsa…
would've saved that demon.
…o iblisi kurtarırdı.
Do you think so?
Öyle mi dersin?
I think he'd like this story.
Bence bu hikâyeyi beğenirdi.
Who's "he"?
Kim?
These books here…
Buradaki kitaplar…
They're all picture books…
Hepsi resimli kitap.
by Jakob Vyrobek, Klaus Poppe, and Emil Schebe.
Jakob Vyrobek, Klaus Poppe ve Emil Schebe imzalı.
The Nameless Monster!
İsimsiz Canavar.
Do you know it?
Biliyor musun?
He wrote many picture books.
Bir sürü kitap yazdı.
Jakob Vyrobek, Klaus Poppe, and Emil Scherbe…
Jakob Vyrobek, Klaus Poppe ve Emil Schebe.
They're all pen names of the same person.
Hepsi aynı kişinin takma isimleri.
A man named Franz Bonaparta.
Franz Bonaparta adlı bir adamın.
Franz Bonaparta…
Franz Bonaparta…
People can become…
İnsanlar istedikleri
whatever they want to be.
her şey olabilir.
Since I wasn't a gifted child, I was kicked out of the book readings.
Yetenekli bir çocuk olmadığım için kitap okuma etkinliğinden atıldım.
Book readings?
Kitap okuma mı?
His book readings were held at the Red Rose Mansion.
Kırmızı Güllü Malikâne'de kitap okuma etkinlikleri düzenlerdi.
I was a student there.
Orada bir öğrenciydim.
I understood what he was trying to do there.
Orada ne yapmaya çalıştığını anladım.
"A deal! Let's make a deal!" said the demon.
"Anlaşalım. Bir anlaşma yapalım" demiş iblis.
"No way! Never!" said the man with big eyes.
"Asla! Hayatta olmaz!" demiş koca gözlü adam.
"Sure, let's make a deal," said the man with a big mouth.
"Tabii, anlaşma yapalım" demiş koca ağızlı adam.
The garden of the man with a big mouth flourished.
Koca ağızlı adamın bahçesi çiçek açmış.
The man with big eyes was so incredibly poor and hungry.
Koca gözlü adam beş parasızmış ve çok açmış.
The man with a big mouth had incredible fun every day.
Koca ağızlı adam her gün gününü gün ediyormuş.
He ate his fill of the fruits of his garden.
Bahçesinin meyveleriyle karnını doyuruyormuş
But he failed to notice that his garden had withered away.
ama bahçesinin solup gittiğini fark edememiş.
In his garden that would never blossom again,
Koca ağızlı adam bir daha çiçek açmayan bahçesinde
"I never should have made a deal with the demon."
"İblisle asla anlaşmamalıydım"
The man with big eyes was so hungry, that he felt as if he would die.
Koca gözlü adam öyle açmış ki öleceğini hissetmiş.
As the tears streamed down his cheeks, he said,
Yanaklarından gözyaşları süzülürken şöyle demiş,
"I should have made a deal with the demon."
"İblisle anlaşma yapmalıydım"
"A deal! Let's make a deal!" said the demon.
"Anlaşalım. Bir anlaşma yapalım" demiş iblis.
The Man with Big Eyes and the Man with a Big Mouth by Jakob Vyrobek.
Jakob Vyrobek'ten Koca Gözlü Adam ve Koca Ağızlı Adam.
Every Friday at 3 p.m., we'd gather for the book reading.
Her cuma saat 3.00'te kitap okuma etkinliği için toplanırdık.
We'd sit around him and listen to him as he reads a book.
Onun etrafında oturur kitap okuyuşunu dinlerdik.
He read in a gentle voice.
Usul bir sesle okurdu.
A very soothing and gentle voice.
Çok rahatlatıcı ve usul bir sesle.
Then after he finished a book, he would ask us this…
Bir kitabı bitirdikten sonra şöyle sorardı…
"The meaning of this story…"
"Bu hikâyenin anlamını…"
Do you understand it?
Anladın mı?
Yes, I do.
Evet, anladım.
I understood too, after reading it multiple times.
Birkaç kez okuduktan sonra ben de anladım.
Then he'd get another picture book.
Sonra başka bir resimli kitap alırdı.
The God of Peace by Klaus Poppe.
Klaus Poppe'den Huzur Tanrısı.
He'd say, "Okay, how about if I read this next?"
Şöyle derdi, "Tamam, şimdi bunu okuyalım mı?"
It's as if this was my first time here.
Sanki buraya ilk kez geliyorum.
Though it's taken quite a long time…
Üzerinden uzun zaman geçse de
all of my memories have come together now.
tüm anılarım şimdi toparlandı.
The God of Peace is always very busy.
Huzur Tanrısı daima çok yoğunmuş.
He was so busy playing the horn, he had no time to look in the mirror.
Kornosunu çalmakla öyle meşgulmüş ki aynaya bakacak vakti yokmuş.
The God of Peace's horn made everyone happy.
Huzur Tanrısı'nın kornosu herkesi mutlu edermiş.
The God of Peace is always very busy.
Huzur Tanrısı daima çok yoğunmuş.
He was so busy scattering magical water that he had no time to look in the mirror.
Sihirli suyu saçmakla öyle meşgulmüş ki aynaya bakacak vakti yokmuş.
The magical water created green mountains, ripened crops, and made flower gardens.
Sihirli su yeşil dağlar yaratırmış,
The God of Peace is always very busy.
Huzur Tanrısı daima çok yoğunmuş.
He was so busy giving everyone names, that he had no time to look in the mirror.
Herkese isim vermekle öyle meşgulmüş ki aynaya bakacak vakti yokmuş.
Your name is "Otto."
Senin adın Otto.
Your name is "Hans."
Senin adın Hans.
Your name is "Thomas."
Senin adın Thomas.
Your name is "Johan."
Senin adın Johan.
To thank him, Johan gave the god his hat.
Johan tanrıya teşekkür etmek için ona şapkasını vermiş.
The god was very happy.
Tanrı çok sevinmiş.
He wanted to see how he looked with the hat on,
Şapkanın nasıl olduğunu görmek isteyince ilk kez aynaya bakmış.
But…
Ama
what he saw in the mirror was a demon.
aynada bir iblis görmüş.
The demon said,
İblis şöyle demiş,
"You are me. I am you."
"Sen bensin, ben de senim"
"Oh dear!"
"Olamaz. Senin gibi bir iblis varken kimse huzur içinde yaşayamaz.
"Oh dear!"
Olamaz"
In distress, the god…
Tanrı telaş içinde…
Do you know what he did?
Ne yapmış biliyor musun?
I know.
Ben biliyorum.
Do you know what the god did next?
Tanrı daha sonra ne yapmış biliyor musun?
I do know.
Biliyorum.
I've finally found you.
Seni nihayet buldum.
I'm home.
Eve geldim.
Welcome back.
Tekrar hoş geldin.
It's me, Mother.
Benim anne.
Even you couldn't tell us apart, Mother.
Sen bile ikimizi ayırt edemiyordun anne.
She was me and I was her.
O bendi, ben de oydum.
You are me and I am you.
Sen bensin, ben de senim.
I understand all of it now.
Artık hepsini anlıyorum.
Where we came from and where we will go.
Nereden geldiğimizi ve nereye gideceğimizi.
The weather outside is wonderful, Mother.
Dışarıda çok güzel bir hava var anne.
Everything will be engulfed in flames.
Her şey alevler içinde kalacak.
I do know.
Biliyorum.
The god will…
Tanrı…
point the gun…
…silahla onun alnına
at his forehead.
nişan alacak.
Shoot me.
Vur beni.
Subtitle translation by: Brian Athey
Alt yazı çevirmeni: Ömür Gencer